<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<root>

    <title>The 22 Best Writing Tips Ever</title>

by <author>Melissa Donovan</author> | <date type="pub">Aug 29, 2023</date> | <topic>Writing Tips</topic> | <comment count="115">115 comments</comment>
]
<text>Today, I’m sharing one of the oldest and most popular posts on <journal type="info">Writing Forward</journal>. This one dates back to <date type="pub">2007</date>, but it’s still one of the most-visited posts on the blog and one of my favorites. I hope you enjoy these writing tips and find them useful! <author type="blogger">Brian Clark</author> over at <business type="blog">Copyblogger</business> issued a challenge to <author type="blogger" count="many">bloggers</author> in the post <post type="blog">“The Cosmo Headline Technique for Blogging Inspiration.”</post> The idea is to use headlines from magazines like <mag>Cosmopolitan</mag> for inspiration, and to write your headlines before composing your article. I’ve taken Brian up on his challenge and as a result, I bring you the <quote>“22 best writing tips ever.”</quote>

<sub>Best Writing Tips</sub>
<cap>These writing tips cover the basics and the most important aspects of writing.</cap>
    
<p num="1">
    
<tip num="1">Do it. Write.</tip>
<tip num="2">Read as much and as often as you can. Remember, every writer is a reader first.</tip>
<tip num="3">Keep a journal or notebook handy at all times so you can jot down all of your brilliant ideas. If you’ve got a smartphone, make sure it’s loaded with a note-taking app. A voice-recording app also comes in handy for recording notes and ideas.</tip>
<tip num="4">Make sure you have a dictionary and thesaurus available whenever you are writing.</tip>
<tip num="5">Be observant. The people and activities that surround you will provide you with great inspiration for characters, plots, and themes.</tip>
<tip num="6">Invest in a few useful resources starting with <book type="info">The Chicago Manual of Style</book> and <book type="info">The Elements of Style</book> (aff links).</tip>
<tip num="7">Grammar: learn the rules and then learn how to break them effectively.</tip>
<tip num="8">Stop procrastinating. Turn off the TV, disconnect from the internet, tune out the rest of the world, sit down, and write.</tip>
<tip num="9">Read works by successful authors to learn what earns a loyal readership.</tip>
<tip num="10">Read works by the canonical authors so you understand what constitutes a respectable literary achievement.</tip>
<tip num="11">Join a writers’ group so you can gain support from the writing community and enjoy camaraderie in your craft.</tip>
<tip num="12">Start a blog. Use it to talk about your own writing process, share your ideas and experiences, or publish your work to a reading audience.</tip>
<tip num="13">Create a space in your home especially for writing.</tip>
<tip num="14">Proofread everything at least three times before submitting your work for publication.</tip>
<tip num="15">Write every single day.</tip>
<tip num="16">Subscribe to blogs about writing. Read them, participate, learn, share, and enjoy!</tip>
<tip num="17">Make it your business to understand grammar and language. Do you know a noun from a verb, a predicate from a preposition? Do you understand tense and verb agreement? You should.</tip>
<tip num="18">Use writing exercises to improve your skills, strengthen your talent, and explore different genres, styles, and techniques.</tip>
<tip num="19">Let go of your inner editor. When you sit down to write a draft, refrain from proofreading until that draft is complete.</tip>
<tip num="20">Allow yourself to write poorly, to write a weak, uninteresting story or a boring, grammatically incorrect poem. You’ll never succeed if you don’t allow yourself a few failures along the way. Do not refrain from writing because you’re worried it won’t be perfect!</tip>
<tip num="21">You are a writer so own it and say it out loud: “I am a writer.” Whether it’s a hobby or your profession, if you write, then you have the right to this title.</tip>
<tip num="22">Write, write, write, and then write some more. Forget everything else and just write.</tip></p>
<closer>Do you think these are the very best writing tips? If you have any tips to add to this list, leave them in the comments!</closer></text>

</root>